woodlandtrust.org.uk 2017-06-24

# Privacy policy | The Woodland Trust

At the Woodland Trust we respect the privacy of our supporters and visitors to our websites. This policy is concerned with how we collect information, what we do with it and what controls you have.

This policy explains how we handle your personal information in connection with our websites, social media pages, and all our printed and electronic communications.

In this policy references to the Woodland Trust, or Trust, or to ‘we’ or ‘us’ are to the Woodland Trust which is a registered charity in England and Wales 294344, and in Scotland SC038885. A non-profit making company limited by guarantee. Registered in England No. 1982873 at Kempton Way, Grantham, Lincolnshire, NG31 6LL.  This also includes our charitable trading company - Woodland Trust (Enterprises) Limited (registered company number 2296645) a wholly owned subsidiary of the Woodland Trust which trades only to raise funds for its parent company – the Woodland Trust.

**What information do we collect?**

We collect various personal information such as name, postal address, telephone number, email address, date of birth (where appropriate), information about your interests and hobbies etc.

We collect this information only in connection with specific activities, such as campaign updates, newsletter requests, registration or membership requests, product purchases, feedback, donations, competition entries, information you provide in public forums on our sites and applications.

The information is either needed to fulfil your request or to enable us to provide you with a more personalised service. You don't have to disclose any of this information to browse our sites. However, if you choose to withhold requested information, we may not be able to provide you with certain services.

The Woodland Trust also uses cookies. Please see “Cookies and how they benefit you” below.

**Where we collect your information?**

We collect your personal information in a number of ways:

  * When you provide it to us directly
  * When you provide permission to other organisations to share it with us (including Facebook or Twitter)
  * When we collect it as you use our websites or apps
  * From publicly available sources (where possible) to keep your information up to date (e.g. the Post Office’s National Change of Address database)

We combine the information from these sources with the information you provide to us directly.

When providing permission for 3rd party organisations to share your data you should check their Privacy Policies carefully to understand fully how they will process your data.

**How will we use your personal information?**

Personal information collected and processed by us may be used, for the following purposes:

  * To provide you with information (including campaigning, volunteering and fundraising), products or services you have requested or which we feel may interest you where you have consented to being contacted
  * To allow you to participate in interactive features on our website, when you choose to do so, e.g. we may help you complete forms by inserting your contact details for you to edit
  * To analyse and improve the services offered on our websites by providing you with the most user-friendly navigation experience we can for your computer or other internet device
  * To process your personal information for the purposes of customer analysis, assessment, profiling and direct marketing, on a personalised or aggregated basis, to help us with our activities and to provide you with the most relevant information.
  * To develop our products, services, systems and relationships with you
  * When we are legally required to hold certain personal information to fulfil statutory obligations, e.g. the collection of Gift Aid.

We will also hold information about your details so that we can respect your preferences for being contacted by us.

**Consent**

On our website when we collect any personal information, you will be given the option to opt-in to receive communications from us by post, mail and telephone.  Where you agree, we may send you information about our conservation, campaigning, membership, services, products, fundraising and other activities and those of other carefully selected organisations.  By providing personal data to us you consent to its use as described in this Privacy Policy.

By entering one of our competitions you will generally be agreeing to receive mailings or emails from the Woodland Trust. 

If at any time you want to alter your preferences or request that we stop communicating with you please let us know by calling us on 0330 333 3300 or sending an email to [enquiries@woodlandtrust.org.uk](mailto:enquiries@woodlandtrust.org.uk)

**Telephone**

We will not make marketing calls to you if you are registered with the Telephone Preference Service (TPS) unless you have given us consent that you are happy to receive calls from us.

You may still receive other types of telephone calls from us as long as they are not marketing calls such as checking your direct debit mandate for example. We do outsource some of the telephone calling we carry out but we will only ever use carefully selected organisations with operate in a sympathetic manner to the Trust.

If you contact us by telephone, your telephone call may be recorded or monitored for the purpose of quality control and for staff training. Any recordings will be held for two years and will then be deleted.

**Who do we share information with?**

We will never sell or rent your personal information to other organisations. We only disclose information when obliged to by law, for purposes of national security, taxation and criminal investigations and the following:

  * If you have agreed that we may do so 
  * When we use other companies to provide services on our behalf, e.g. processing, mailing or delivering orders, answering customers’ questions about products or services, sending mail and emails, customer analysis, assessment and profiling, when using auditors/advisors or processing credit/debit card payments 
  * To our subsidiaries (i.e. the companies owned by the Woodland Trust)
  * If we receive a complaint about any content you have posted or transmitted to or from one of our sites, to enforce or apply our Terms & Conditions or if we believe that we need to do so to protect and defend the rights, property or personal safety of the Woodland Trust, our websites or our visitors and for other lawful purposes
  * If we merge with another organisation to form a new entity, information may be transferred to the new entity
  * We may disclose aggregate statistics about our site visitors, supporters, customers and sales to describe our services and operations to prospective partners, advertisers and other reputable third parties and for other lawful purposes, but these statistics won’t include any personally identifying information
  * If we run an event in partnership with other named organisations your details may need to be shared. We will be very clear what will happen to your data when you register.

**Storing your information**

Information which you submit to us is sent to computers located in the United Kingdom. This is necessary in order to process the information and to send you the information you have requested.

Information submitted by you may be transferred by us to our other offices and other reputable third party organisations as referred to in this policy and these maybe situated outside of the European Economic Area (EEA). This will be done in accordance with guidance issued by the Information Commissioner’s Office.

Any personal information you supply to us will not be retained for longer than necessary.

**Children**

If you are aged under 16, please ensure you obtain your parent/guardian's consent before sending any personal information to any website or the Woodland Trust.

We do have activities for those under 16 so we may ask your age. Prior to taking part in these please ensure you speak to your parent or guardian.

Please note that we will not knowingly accept online donations or orders for goods or services from persons aged under 16 years.

We encourage you to be aware of the activities in which your children are participating, both offline and online. If your children voluntarily disclose information, this may encourage unsolicited messages. We suggest that you discourage your child from providing any information without your consent.

**Access to your own information**

You can contact us anytime to change or update the details we hold. You can obtain a copy of your record (this is known as Subject Access Request), please note that we reserve the right to charge a fee of £10 for any such request. We will of course ask you to confirm your identity. If you would like to access your personal data held by the Woodland Trust please apply in writing to:

Data Protection Officer  
The Woodland Trust  
Kempton Way  
Grantham  
NG31 6LL

**Other websites**

Our websites contains hyperlinks to many other websites. This privacy policy only applies to this website so when you link to other websites you should read their own privacy policies.

Please let us know if a link is not working (use the 'Contact us' link which can be found at the bottom of every webpage).

In purchasing goods or services from any of the companies to which any Woodland Trust sites links, you are forming a contract with the company(s) concerned (agreeing to their terms and conditions), not the Woodland Trust.

**Using our social media pages**

While this statement covers our privacy practices and how we will use any information collected from our websites and social media pages, it doesn’t cover how providers of social media websites will use your information.

You should read the social media site’s privacy policies before adding any content to our social media pages. Make use of the social media site privacy settings and reporting mechanisms to control the way that your information is handled.

**Posting content on our websites and social media pages**

Remember that the internet provides instant worldwide access. Any information that you provide will be worldwide instantly.

We don’t moderate our websites. So if you post comments about other people it’s not only your privacy that is at stake. Protect your friends’ privacy and reputations. Be careful about uploading any content that may show you or your friends in compromising situations and be aware that other users may abuse the content you have provided.

Please don’t provide information about yourself or other people unless you’re sure you and they are happy to have it made public. In particular, don’t provide any information about others without their consent where that information might identify them, such as:-

  * Names 
  * Tagged photos
  * Location

Under no circumstances make public other peoples’ home address, email addresses or contact numbers.

**Security**

We have security measures in place to attempt to protect against the loss, misuse and alteration of personal information under our control. Whilst we can’t ensure or guarantee that loss, misuse or alteration of information won’t occur, we’ll use standard industry methods to prevent this.

Unfortunately, the transmission of information across the internet isn’t completely secure and whilst we do our best to try to protect the security of your information we can’t ensure or guarantee that loss, misuse or alteration of information won’t occur whilst you or we are transferring this information.

Where you or we have provided a password enabling you to access parts of our websites or use our services, it’s your responsibility to keep this password confidential. Please don’t share your password with anyone.

**Volunteering**

If you register to become a volunteer we will use your information to process your application, update you with the latest news about our work, for administration, for fundraising, update you with how you can get involved and to ensure that you are receiving the right information.

**Cookies and how they benefit you**

Our website uses cookies, as almost all websites do, to help provide you with the best experience we can. Cookies are small text files that are placed on your computer or mobile phone when you browse websites

Our cookies help us:

  * Make our website work as you'd expect
  * Remember your settings during and between visits
  * Improve the speed/security of the site
  * Allow you to share pages with social networks like Facebook
  * Continuously improve our website for you
  * Make our marketing more efficient (ultimately helping us to offer the service we do at the price we do)

**Granting us permission to use cookies**

If the settings on your browser that you are using to view this website are adjusted to accept cookies we take this, and your continued use of our website, to mean that you are fine with this. Should you wish to remove or not use cookies from our site you can learn how to do this below, however doing so will likely mean that our site will not work as you would expect.

**How long do cookies last?**

When a web server sends a cookie, it asks your browser to keep that particular cookie until a certain date and time. These dates can be:

  * Some date in the future - Might be a few minutes or a few hours from now (to track something like your shopping cart in an online store). The cookie might expire many years in the future, to keep track of your browser for a long time
  * When you close your browser - Called a session cookie, the next time you start your browser these will have vanished
  * Some date in the past - This is how the server asks a browser to remove a previously-stored cookie

**Our own cookies**

We use cookies to make our website work including:

  * Remembering if you have accepted our terms and conditions
  * Allowing you to add comments to our site
  * Remembering if we have already asked you certain questions (e.g. you declined to use our app or take our survey)

There is no way to prevent these cookies being set other than to not use our site.

**Site improvement cookies**

We regularly test new designs or site features on our sites. We may do this by showing slightly different versions of our websites to different people and anonymously monitoring how our site visitors respond to these different versions. Ultimately this helps us to offer you a better website experience.

**Anonymous visitor statistics cookies**

We use cookies to compile visitor statistics such as how many people have visited our website, what type of technology they are using, how long they spend on the site, what page they look at, etc. This helps us to continuously improve our website. These analytics programs also tell us, on an anonymous basis, how people reached this site (e.g. from a search engine) and whether they have been here before, helping us to to develop our services for you. Our site uses the following analytics programmes:

**Advertising or Targeting cookies**

These types of cookies are used to deliver adverts which will be more relevant to you and your interests. They are also used to limit the number of times you see an advertisement and to help measure the effectiveness of the advertising campaign. They are normally placed by advertising networks with the Trust's permission. They remember that you have visited a website and this information is shared with other organisations such as advertisers. Targeting or advertising cookies will often be linked to site functionality provided by the other organisation.

We use 'Advertising' cookies on Woodland Trust websites to:

  * Link to social networks, like Facebook, who may use information to provide targeted advertising to you on other websites
  * Used to identify that you have visited a Woodland Trust website, to show you relevant adverts from us
  * Provide advertising networks with information on your visit so that they can present you with adverts that you may be interested in

**Third party functions**

Our site, like most websites, includes functionality provided by third parties. A common example is an embedded YouTube video. Our site includes the following third part functions which use cookies:

  * [YouTube](http://www.youtube.com/ "YouTube \(Opens in a new window\)")
  * [Twitter](https://twitter.com/ "Twitter \(Opens in a new window\)")

Disabling these cookies will likely break the functions offered by these third parties

**Social website cookies**

So you can easily "Like" or "Share" our content on social network sites, we have sharing buttons on our site from:

The privacy implications on this will vary from social network to social network and will be dependent on the privacy settings you have chosen on these networks.

**Turning Cookies off**

You can usually switch cookies off by adjusting your browser settings to stop it from accepting cookies. Doing so, however, will likely limit the functionality of ours and a large proportion of the world's websites as cookies are a standard part of most modern websites.

It may be that your concerns around cookies relate to so called "spyware". Rather than switching off cookies in your browser you may find that anti-spyware software achieves the same objective by automatically deleting cookies considered to be invasive.

**Notification of change of Privacy and cookie policy**

We keep our privacy policy under regular review and we will place any updates on this webpage. Your continued use of any of our websites after changes are posted constitutes your acceptance of these Terms and Conditions.

This Privacy and Cookie Policy was last updated: December 2016

**Your acceptance of this policy**

By using our sites or social media pages, or by entering a competition or raffle, you consent to our collection and use of information in accordance with this policy. If you don’t agree to this policy, please don’t use our sites or social media pages or enter our competitions or raffles.

**How to contact us**

If you wish to talk to use about anything in the policy or the information we hold about you please contact our Supporter Services team:

  * by telephone: 0330 333 3300
  * or by email: [enquiries@woodlandtrust.org.uk](mailto:enquiries@woodlandtrust.org.uk) 
  * or by post: Supporter Services, Woodland Trust, Kempton Way, Grantham, Lincolnshire, NG31 6LL

Please note that calls to our Supporter Services team may be monitored or recorded.
